Good morning.
صباح الخير
My name is Eric Li, and I was born here.
اسمي إريك لي، وقد ولدت هنا.
But no, I wasn't born there.
لكن لا. لم أولد هناك.
This was where I was born:
هنا حيث ولدت:
Shanghai, at the height of the Cultural Revolution.
شانغاي، في ذروة الثروة الثقافية.
My grandmother tells me that she heard
أخبرتني جدتي أنها سمعت
the sound of gunfire along with my first cries.
صوت إطلاق النار إلى جانب صرخاتي الأولى.
When I was growing up, I was told a story
عندما كنت أترعرع، قيلت لي قصة
that explained all I ever needed to know about humanity.
والتي شرحت لي كل ما احتجت إلى معرفته حول الإنسانية.
It went like this.
وصار الأمر على هذا النحو.
All human societies develop in linear progression,
تتطور كل المجتمعات الإنسانية في تقدم خطي،
beginning with primitive society, then slave society,
بدءاً بالمجتمع الفطري، ثم المجتمع العبودي،
feudalism, capitalism, socialism,
والإقطاعي، والرأسمالي والإشتراكي
and finally, guess where we end up?
وأخيراً، خمّن إلى أين وصل بنا الحال؟
Communism!
الشيوعية!
Sooner or later, all of humanity,
عاجلاً أو آجلاً، البشرية جمعاء،
regardless of culture, language, nationality,
بغض النظر عن الثقافة، واللغة والجنسية
will arrive at this final stage
ستصل إلى هذه المرحلة الأخيرة
of political and social development.
من التطور السياسي والإجتماعي.
The entire world's peoples will be unified
ستكون جميع شعوب العالم متحدة
in this paradise on Earth
في جنة الأرض هذه
and live happily ever after.
وسيعيشون في سعادة دائمة.
But before we get there, we're engaged
لكن قبل أن نصل إلى ذلك، نحن منخرطون
in a struggle between good and evil,
في صراع بين الخير والشر،
the good of socialism against the evil of capitalism,
وخير الاشتراكية ضد شر الرأسمالية،
and the good shall triumph.
والنصر للخير.
That, of course, was the meta-narrative
وهذه، بالطبع، كانت الأفكار الإنسانية الكبرى
distilled from the theories of Karl Marx.
المستخلصة من نظريات كارل ماركس.
And the Chinese bought it.
واشتراها الصينيون.
We were taught that grand story day in and day out.
كما تم تعليمنا تلك القصة الكبرى يوماً بعد يوم.
It became part of us, and we believed in it.
أصبحت جزءاً منا، وقد آمنّا بها.
The story was a bestseller.
وكانت القصة من أكثر الكتب مبيعاً.
About one third of the entire world's population
حوالي ثلث سكان العالم أجمع
lived under that meta-narrative.
عاشوا تحت تلك النظريات الكبرى.
Then, the world changed overnight.
وبعدئذٍ، تغير العالم بين ليلةٍ وضحاها.
As for me, disillusioned by the failed religion of my youth,
بالنسبة لي، بسبب خيبة أملي من الدين الذي اعتقنته في شبابي،
I went to America and became a Berkeley hippie.
ذهبت إلى أمريكا وأصبحت من "هيبيز" بيركلي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, as I was coming of age, something else happened.
والآن، بينما كنت أناهز سن الرشد، شيءٌ آخر قد حدث.
As if one big story wasn't enough,
كما لو أن قصة واحدة كبيرة لم تكن كافية،
I was told another one.
قيلت لي قصة أخرى.
This one was just as grand.
وهذه القصة هي قصة كبرى أيضاً.
It also claims that all human societies
إنها تدعي أيضاً أن كل المجتمعات الإنسانية
develop in a linear progression towards a singular end.
تتطور في تقدم طولي باتجاه نهاية فردية.
This one went as follows:
جرت هذه القصة كما يلي:
All societies, regardless of culture,
كل المجتمعات، بغض النظر عن الثقافة،
be it Christian, Muslim, Confucian,
سواء كانت مسيحية أو مسلمة أو كونفوشيوسية،
must progress from traditional societies
يجب أن تتقدم من مجتمعات تقليدية
in which groups are the basic units
تكون فيها الجماعات هي الوحدات الأساسية
to modern societies in which atomized individuals
إلى مجتمعات حديثة يكون فيها الأفراد المتفككين
are the sovereign units,
هم الوحدات ذات السيادة،
and all these individuals are, by definition, rational,
وكل أولئك الأفراد، بحكم التعريف، عقلانييون
and they all want one thing:
وجميعهم يريدون شيء واحد:
the vote.
الاقتراع.
Because they are all rational, once given the vote,
ولأنهم كلهم عقلانييون، حينما يُنتخب أحدهم،
they produce good government
فإنهم ينتجون حكومة جيدة
and live happily ever after.
ويعيشون في سعادة دائمة.
Paradise on Earth, again.
الجنة على الأرض، مرة أخرى.
Sooner or later, electoral democracy will be
عاجلاً أم آجلاً، ستكون الديموقراطية الانتخابية
the only political system for all countries and all peoples,
النظام السياسي الوحيد لكل الدول ولكل الشعوب،
with a free market to make them all rich.
مع سوق حرة لجعلهم كلهم أغنياء.
But before we get there, we're engaged in a struggle
لكن قبل أن نصل إلى ذلك، نحن منخرطون في صراع
between good and evil.
بين الخير والشر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The good belongs to those who are democracies
الخير ينتمي للدول الديموقراطية
and are charged with a mission of spreading it
والمكلفة بمهمة نشر الديقراطية
around the globe, sometimes by force,
حول العالم، أحياناً بالقوة،
against the evil of those who do not hold elections.
ضد شر تلك الدول التي لا تعقد انتخابات.
(Video) George H.W. Bush: A new world order...
جوروج إتش.دبليو بوش: نظام عالمي جديد ...
(Video) George W. Bush:... ending tyranny in our world...
جورج دبليو. بوش: ... إنهاء الاستبداد في عالمنا ...
(Video) Barack Obama:... a single standard for all
باراك أوباما: ... معيار وحيد لكل
Eric X. Li: Now --
إريك إكس. لي: الآن --
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
This story also became a bestseller.
أصبحت هذه القصة أيضاً من أكثر القصص رواجاً.
According to Freedom House,
وفقاً لمؤسسة Freedom House،
the number of democracies went from 45 in 1970
صعد عدد الدول الديموقراطية من 45 دولة في عام 1970
to 115 in 2010.
إلى 115 في عام 2010.
In the last 20 years, Western elites tirelessly
في العشرين سنة الأخيرة، كانت النخب الغربية
trotted around the globe selling this prospectus:
تهرول دول كلل أو ملل في جميع أنحاء العالم لبيع هذا البيان:
Multiple parties fight for political power
نضال الأحزاب المتعددة من أجل القوة السياسية
and everyone voting on them
وتصويت الجميع لهم
is the only path to salvation
هو الطريق الوحيد لخلاص
to the long-suffering developing world.
العالم النامي الذي طالت معاناته.
Those who buy the prospectus are destined for success.
من يشتري ذلك البيان مقدّر له النجاح.
Those who do not are doomed to fail.
ومن لا يشتريه محكوم عليه بالفشل.
But this time, the Chinese didn't buy it.
لكن هذه المرة، لم يشتريه الصينيون.
Fool me once...
لا تخدعني مرتين ...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The rest is history.
الباقي هو التاريخ.
In just 30 years, China went from
في ثلاثين عاماً فقط، انتقلت الصين من
one of the poorest agricultural countries in the world
واحدة من أفقر الدول الزراعية في العالم
to its second-largest economy.
إلى ثاني أكبر اقتصاد في العالم.
Six hundred fifty million people
ست مائة وخمسين مليون شخص
were lifted out of poverty.
تم انتشالهم من الفقر.
Eighty percent of the entire world's poverty alleviation
80% من تخفيف حدة الفقر في العالم بأسره
during that period happened in China.
خلال تلك الفترة حصل في الصين.
In other words, all the new and old democracies
بعبارة أخرى، كل الدول الديموقراطية الجديدة والقديمة
put together amounted to a mere fraction
مجتمعة وصلت إلى مجرد جزء بسيط
of what a single, one-party state did without voting.
من ما فعلته دولة منفردة بحزب واحد من دون اقتراع.
See, I grew up on this stuff: food stamps.
كما ترى، نشأت على هذا الشيء: طوابع الطعام.
Meat was rationed to a few hundred grams
كان يتم تقنين اللحوم إلى بضع مئات من الجرامات
per person per month at one point.
للشخص الواحد في الشهر في وقت محدد.
Needless to say, I ate all my grandmother's portions.
وغني عن القول، فقد أكلت كل حصص جدتي.
So I asked myself, what's wrong with this picture?
لذا سألت نفسي: "ما الخطأ في هذه الصورة؟"
Here I am in my hometown,
أنا هنا في مسقط رأسي،
my business growing leaps and bounds.
عملي التجاري ينمو بشكل سريع.
Entrepreneurs are starting companies every day.
يقوم روّاد الأعمال بتأسيس شركات كل يوم.
Middle class is expanding in speed and scale
الطبقة الوسطى تتزايد بسرعة وبمدى
unprecedented in human history.
لم يسبق لهما مثيل في تاريخ البشرية.
Yet, according to the grand story,
إلا أنه، وتبعاً للقصة الكبيرة،
none of this should be happening.
لاشئ من هذا يجب أن يحدث
So I went and did the only thing I could. I studied it.
لذا ذهبت وفعلت الشيء الوحيد الذي استطعت فعله. لقد درستها.
Yes, China is a one-party state
نعم، الصين هي دولة الحزب الواحد
run by the Chinese Communist Party, the Party,
التي يحكمها الحزب الشيوعي الصيني، "الحزب"،
and they don't hold elections.
ولا يعقدون انتخابات.
Three assumptions are made
هناك ثلاث افتراضات تفترضها
by the dominant political theories of our time.
وفقاً للنظريات السياسية السائدة في عصرنا.
Such a system is operationally rigid,
نظام كهذا هو نظام جامد وظيفياً،
politically closed, and morally illegitimate.
ومنغلق سياسياً وأخلاقياً غير شرعي.
Well, the assumptions are wrong.
حسناً، هذه الافتراضات خاطئة.
The opposites are true.
عكسها هو الصحيح.
Adaptability, meritocracy, and legitimacy
التكيفية ، الجدارة ، الشرعية
are the three defining characteristics
هي الخصائص الثلاثة المميزة
of China's one-party system.
لنظام الحزب الواحد الصيني.
Now, most political scientists will tell us
الآن، سيخبرنا معظم العلماء السياسيين
of self-correction.
على التقويم الذاتي.
It won't last long because it cannot adapt.
ولن يستمر طويلاً لأنه غير قادر على التكيف.
Now here are the facts.
وإليك الحقائق.
In 64 years of running the largest country in the world,
في الأربعة وستين عاماً من حكم أكبر دولة في العالم،
the range of the Party's policies has been wider
كان مجال سياسات "الحزب" أوسع
than any other country in recent memory,
من أي دولة أخرى في الذاكرة الحديثة،
from radical land collectivization to the Great Leap Forward,
من مشروع إقامة المزارع الجماعية الجذري إلى مشروع "القفزة الكبرى للأمام"،
then privatization of farmland,
ثم خصخصة الأراضي الزراعية،
then the Cultural Revolution,
ثم الثورة الثقافية،
then Deng Xiaoping's market reform,
ثم إصلاح دنغ شياو بينغ للسوق،
then successor Jiang Zemin took the giant political step
من ثم، اتخذ خليفته جيانغ تسه مين الخطوة السياسية العملاقة
of opening up Party membership to private businesspeople,
المتمثلة في فتح عضوية "الحزب" لرجال أعمال خاصين،
something unimaginable during Mao's rule.
وهو أمر لا يمكن تصوره أثناء حكم ماو.
So the Party self-corrects in rather dramatic fashions.
فالحزب يقَّوم ذاته بأساليب مثيرة نوعاً ما.
Institutionally, new rules get enacted
مؤسسياً، يتم سنّ قوانين جديدة
to correct previous dysfunctions.
لتصحيح الاختلالات السابقة.
For example, term limits.
مثلاً، حدود مدة الوظيفة.
Political leaders used to retain their positions for life,
اعتاد القادة السياسيين على الاحتفاظ بمناصبهم مدى الحياة
and they used that to accumulate power
وكانوا يستغلون ذلك لتكديس السلطة
and perpetuate their rules.
ولإدامة حكمهم.
Mao was the father of modern China,
كان ماو أب الصين الحديثة،
yet his prolonged rule led to disastrous mistakes.
إلا أن فترة حكمه الطويلة أدت إلى أخطاء كارثية.
So the Party instituted term limits
لذلك وضع "الحزب" حدود مدة الوظيفة
with mandatory retirement age of 68 to 70.
بتحديد سن تقاعد إلزامي من 68 إلى 70.
One thing we often hear is,
أحد الأمور التي نسمعها هي،
"Political reforms have lagged far behind economic reforms,"
"تباطأت الإصلاحات السياسية كثيراً عن الإصلاحات الاقتصادية،"
and "China is in dire need of political reform."
و "الصين في حاجة ماسة للإصلاح السياسي."
But this claim is a rhetorical trap
لكن هذا الإدعاء عبارة عن فخ خطابي
hidden behind a political bias.
مخفي خلف الانحياز السياسي.
See, some have decided a priori
كما ترون، قرر بعضهم مسبقاً
what kinds of changes they want to see,
أنواع التغييرات التي يريدون رؤيتها،
and only such changes can be called political reform.
وتلك التغييرات فقط هي ما يمكن أن يُطلق عليه إصلاح سياسي.
The truth is, political reforms have never stopped.
الحقيقة هي، الإصلاحات السياسية لم تتوقف أبداً.
Compared with 30 years ago, 20 years, even 10 years ago,
مقارنة بثلاثين عاماً مضت، عشرين عاماً، أو حتى عشرة أعوام مضت،
every aspect of Chinese society,
كل جانب من المجتمع الصيني،
how the country is governed,
كيف تُدار البلاد،
from the most local level to the highest center,
من أكثر المستويات محلية إلى أعلى مركز،
are unrecognizable today.
لا يمكن فهمها بسهولة اليوم.
Now such changes are simply not possible
مثل هذه التغييرات الآن غير ممكنة تماماً
without political reforms of the most fundamental kind.
من دون الاصلاحات السياسية ذات النوع الأكثر جوهرية.
Now I would venture to suggest the Party
الآن سأجرؤ على أن أشير إلى أن "الحزب"
is the world's leading expert in political reform.
هو الخبير في الإصلاح السياسي الرائد في العالم.
The second assumption is that in a one-party state,
الافتراض الثاني هو أنه في الدولة ذات الحزب الواحد،
power gets concentrated in the hands of the few,
تتمركز السلطة في أيدي قلة من الناس،
and bad governance and corruption follow.
ويتبع ذلك سوء الإدارة والفساد.
Indeed, corruption is a big problem,
بالفعل، الفساد مشكلة كبيرة.
but let's first look at the larger context.
لكن دعنا ننظر فقط إلى السياق الأكبر.
Now, this may be counterintuitive to you.
الآن، قد يكون ذلك مخالف لتوقعاتك.
The Party happens to be one of the most meritocratic
يصادف الحزب أن يكون واحداً من المؤسسات
political institutions in the world today.
السياسية الأكثر جدارة في العالم اليوم.
China's highest ruling body, the Politburo, has 25 members.
يضم أعلى جهاز حاكم في الصين، الـمكتب السياسي (بوليتبورو)، 25 عضو.
In the most recent one, only five of them
في آخر مكتب، خمسة فقط منهم
came from a background of privilege, so-called princelings.
جاؤوا من خلفية مميزة، تسمى بالأمير الصغير.
The other 20, including the president and the premier,
العشرون عضو المتبقين، بما فيهم الرئيس ورئيس الوزراء،
came from entirely ordinary backgrounds.
جاؤوا من خلفيات عادية تماماً.
In the larger central committee of 300 or more,
في اللجنة المركزية الأكبر المكونة من 300 عضو أو أكثر،
the percentage of those who were born
نسبة أولئك الذين ولدوا
into power and wealth was even smaller.
في طبقة ثرية ونافذة كانت أصغر.
The vast majority of senior Chinese leaders
الغالبية العظمى من كبار القادة الصينيين
worked and competed their way to the top.
عملوا وتنافسوا للوصول للقمة.
Compare that with the ruling elites
قارن ذلك بالنخب الحاكمة
in both developed and developing countries,
في كلٍ من البلدان المتقدمة والنامية،
I think you'll find the Party being near the top
أعتقد أنك ستجد "الحزب" قريب من القمة
in upward mobility.
بحركة تصاعدية.
The question then is, how could that be possible
السؤال إذن هو، كيف يمكن أن يكون ذلك ممكناً
in a system run by one party?
في نظام يُدار بحزب واحد؟
Now we come to a powerful political institution,
والأن نأتي إلى مؤسسة سياسية قوية،
little-known to Westerners:
لا يعرفها الغربيون كثيراً:
the Party's Organization Department.
إدارة تنظيم الحزب.
The department functions like a giant
تعمل الإدارة كمحرك
human resource engine that would be the envy
عملاق للموارد البشرية الذي قد يُحسد
of even some of the most successful corporations.
من قبل بعض أهم الشركات الناجحة.
It operates a rotating pyramid
تقوم بإدارة هرم دوّار
made up of three components:
مكون من ثلاث عناصر:
civil service, state-owned enterprises,
الخدمة المدنية، والشركات المملوكة للدولة،
and social organizations like a university
والمنظمات الاجتماعية كالجامعة
or a community program.
أو البرامج المجتمعية.
They form separate yet integrated career paths
وتشكل هذه العناصر مسارات وظيفية منفصلة لكن مندمجة
for Chinese officials.
للموظفين الصينيين.
They recruit college grads into entry-level positions
يقومون بتوظيف خريجي الجامعات في وظائف متدنية الرتبة
in all three tracks, and they start from the bottom,
في جميع المسارات الثلاثة، ويبدأون من الأدنى،
called "keyuan" [clerk].
ويدعى "كويان" [محرّر].
Then they could get promoted
وقد يحصلون على ترقية
through four increasingly elite ranks:
من خلال أربعة مراتب متميزة أكثر فأكثر:
fuke [deputy section manager], ke [section manager], fuchu [deputy division manager], and chu [division manger].
فوكا [نائب مدير قسم]، كا [مدير قسم]، فوتشو [نائب مدير شعبة] وتشو [مدير شعبة]
Now these are not moves from "Karate Kid," okay?
والآن هذه ليست حركات من فيلم "Karate Kid"، حسناً؟
It's serious business.
إنها عمل جاد.
The range of positions is wide,
نطاق الوظائف عريض،
from running health care in a village
من إدارة الرعاية الصحية في قرية
to foreign investment in a city district
إلى الاستثمار الأجنبي في حي أحد المدن
to manager in a company.
إلى مدير في شركة.
Once a year, the department reviews their performance.
مرة كل سنة، تقوم الإدارة بمراجعة أدائهم.
They interview their superiors, their peers,
يقومون بإجراء مقابلات مع رؤسائهم، وأقرانهم
their subordinates. They vet their personal conduct.
ومرؤوسيهم. يقومون بفحص سلوكهم الشخصي.
They conduct public opinion surveys.
ويجرون استطلاعات للرأي العام.
Then they promote the winners.
ثم يقومون بترقية الفائزين.
Throughout their careers, these cadres
طوال حياتهم المهنية، يمكن لهذه الكوادر
can move through and out of all three tracks.
أن تنتقل عبر أو خارج جميع المسارات الثلاث.
Over time, the good ones move beyond the four base levels
ومع مرور الوقت، يتجاوز الجيدون المستويات الأربعة الأساسية
to the fuju [deputy bureau chief] and ju [bureau chief] levels.
إلى مستويات فوجو [نائب رئيس مكتب] وجو [رئيس مكتب].
There, they enter high officialdom.
هناك، يدخلون طبقة الموظفين العاليا.
By that point, a typical assignment will be
عند تلك المرحلة، ستكون المهمة النموذجية
to manage a district with a population in the millions
إدارة منطقة سكانها بالملايين
or a company with hundreds of millions of dollars in revenue.
أو إدراة شركة بعائد يبلغ مئات الملايين من الدولارات.
Just to show you how competitive the system is,
وفقط كي أريك كيف تبدو تنافسية هذا النظام،
in 2012, there were 900,000 fuke and ke levels,
في 2012، كان هناك 900,000 مستوى لفوكا [نائب مدير قسم] و كا [مدير قسم]،
600,000 fuchu and chu levels,
و 600.000 لفوتشو [نائب مدير شعبة] وتشو [مدير شعبة]
and only 40,000 fuju and ju levels.
و 40,000 مستوى فقط لفوجو [نائب مدير مكتب] وجو [مدير مكتب].
After the ju levels,
بعد مستويات "جو"،
the best few move further up several more ranks,
القلة الأفضل يصعدون لعدة مراتب،
and eventually make it to the Central Committee.
وأخيراً ينجحون في الوصول لـ "اللجنة المركزية".
The process takes two to three decades.
تستغرق العملية عقدين أو ثلاث عقود.
Does patronage play a role? Yes, of course.
هل تلعب المحسوبية دوراً؟ نعم، بالطبع.
But merit remains the fundamental driver.
لكن تظل الجدارة هي المحرك الأساسي.
In essence, the Organization Department runs
في الأساس، تستخدم "إدارة التنظيم"
a modernized version of China's centuries-old
نسخة حديثة من نظام التوجيه الصيني
mentoring system.
المتبع منذ قرون.
China's new president, Xi Jinping,
رئيس الصين الجديد، شي جين بينغ،
is the son of a former leader, which is very unusual,
هو ابن لقائد سابق،الذي كان استثنائياً،
first of his kind to make the top job.
الأول من نوعه الذي يصل لأعلى منصب.
Even for him, the career took 30 years.
حتى في حالته، استغرقت مهنته 30 عاماً.
He started as a village manager,
بدأ كمدير قرية،
and by the time he entered the Politburo,
وبمرور الوقت دخل إلى الـ "بوليتبورو"،
he had managed areas with a total population
وقد أدار مناطق بلغ مجموع سكانها
of 150 million people
150 مليون نسمة
and combined GDPs of 1.5 trillion U.S. dollars.
وبنواتج محلية إجمالية مجموعة تبلغ 1.5 مليون تريليون دولار أمريكي.
Now, please don't get me wrong, okay?
والآن، من فضلكم لا تُسيئوا فهمي، حسناً؟
This is not a put-down of anyone. It's just a statement of fact.
هذا ليس تقليلاً من أي أحد. هو فقط عرض واقعة.
George W. Bush, remember him?
جوروج دبليو. بوش، هل تذكرونه؟
This is not a put-down.
هذا ليس إذلالاً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Before becoming governor of Texas,
قبل أن يصبح حاكماً لتكساس،
or Barack Obama before running for president,
أو قبل أن يترشح باراك أوباما للرئاسة،
could not make even a small county manager
لم يتمكنا حتى من أن يديرا مقاطعة صغيرة
in China's system.
في النظام الصيني.
Winston Churchill once said that democracy
وينستون تشرتشل قال مرة أن الديموقراطية
is a terrible system except for all the rest.
هي نظام مريع باستثناء البقية.
Well, apparently he hadn't heard of the Organization Department.
حسناً، من الواضح أنه لم يسمع بـ "إدارة التنظيم".
Now, Westerners always assume that
الآن، دائماً يفترض الغربيون أن
multi-party election with universal suffrage
الانتخابات متعددة الأحزاب التي تجرى بالاقتراع العالم
is the only source of political legitimacy.
هي المصدر الوحيد للشرعية السياسية.
I was asked once, "The Party wasn't voted in by election.
سُئلت مرة: "لم يتم ترشيح الحزب عن طريق الانتخابات.
Where is the source of legitimacy?"
إذاً أين هو مصدر الشرعية؟"
I said, "How about competency?"
قلت: "ماذا عن الكفاءة؟"
We all know the facts.
كلنا نعرف الحقائق.
In 1949, when the Party took power,
في عام 1949، عندما تولى "الحزب" السلطة،
China was mired in civil wars, dismembered by foreign aggression,
كانت الصين غارقة في الحروب الأهلية، وممزقة من قبل العدوان الأجنبي،
average life expectancy at that time, 41 years old.
كان متوسط العمر المتوقع في ذلك الوقت 41 سنة.
Today, it's the second largest economy in the world,
اليوم، هي ثاني أكبر اقتصاد في العالم،
an industrial powerhouse, and its people live
وتمثل قوة صناعية، ويعيش شعبها
in increasing prosperity.
في رخاء متزايد.
Pew Research polls Chinese public attitudes,
استطلع مركز بيو للدراسات اتجاهات الجمهور الصيني،
and here are the numbers in recent years.
وإليكم الأرقام في السنوات الاخيرة.
Satisfaction with the direction of the country: 85 percent.
الرضا عن توجه الدولة: 85%.
Those who think they're better off than five years ago:
من يعتقدون أنهم أفضل حالاً مما كانوا عليه قبل خمس سنوات:
70 percent.
70%.
Those who expect the future to be better:
من يتوقعون أن المستقبل سيكون أفضل:
a whopping 82 percent.
نسبة هائلة تصل لـ 82%.
Financial Times polls global youth attitudes,
أجرت صحيفة Financial Times استطلاعاً لاتجاهات الشباب العالمي،
and these numbers, brand new, just came from last week.
وهذه الأرقام، الحديثة جداً، ظهرت الأسبوع الماضي.
Ninety-three percent of China's Generation Y
93% من جيل الألفية في الصين
are optimistic about their country's future.
متفائلون بشأن مستقبل بلادهم.
Now, if this is not legitimacy, I'm not sure what is.
والآن إن لم تكن هذه شرعية، فلست متأكداً من ماهيتها.
In contrast, most electoral democracies around the world
في المقابل، معظم الديموقراطيات الانتخابية حول العالم
are suffering from dismal performance.
تعاني من الأداء السيء.
I don't need to elaborate for this audience
لا أحتاج أن أفسر لهذا الحضور
how dysfunctional it is, from Washington to European capitals.
مدى اختلال ذلك النظام، من واشنطن إلى العواصم الأوروبية.
With a few exceptions, the vast number
مع بعض الاستثناءات، العدد الهائل
of developing countries that have adopted electoral regimes
من الدول النامية التي اعتمدت الأنظمة الانتخابية
are still suffering from poverty and civil strife.
لا تزال تعاني من الفقر والحروب الأهلية.
Governments get elected, and then they fall
يتم انتخاب الحكومات، ثم ينخفض
below 50 percent approval in a few months
تأييد الشعب لها إلى أدنى من 50% في شهور قليلة
and stay there and get worse until the next election.
ويظلون في مناصبهم ويزداد أدائهم سوءاً حتى تحين الانتخابات القادمة.
Democracy is becoming a perpetual cycle
أصبحت الديموقراطية دورة دائمة
of elect and regret.
من الانتخاب والتراجع.
At this rate, I'm afraid it is democracy,
بهذا المعدل، أخشى أن تكون هذه ديموقراطية،
not China's one-party system, that is in danger
ليس نظام الحزب الواحد الصيني، الذي يُعد مخاطرة
of losing legitimacy.
لفقدان الشرعية.
Now, I don't want to create the misimpression
الآن، لا أريد أن أصنع الانطباع الخاطئ
that China's hunky-dory, on the way
بأن الصين رائعة، وأنها في طريقها نحو
to some kind of superpowerdom.
تحقيق نوعاً من القوة العظمى.
The country faces enormous challenges.
تواجه الحكومة تحديات هائلة.
The social and economic problems that come
المشاكل الاجتماعية والاقتصادية التي تأتي
with wrenching change like this are mind-boggling.
مع تغيير عنيف كهذا تحير العقل.
Pollution is one. Food safety. Population issues.
التلوث مشكلة واحدة. سلامة الأغذية. قضايا السكان.
On the political front, the worst problem is corruption.
على الجبهة السياسية، المشكلة الأسوأ هي الفساد.
Corruption is widespread and undermines the system
الفساد منتشر على نطاق واسع ويضعف النظام
and its moral legitimacy.
وشرعيته الأخلاقية.
But most analysts misdiagnose the disease.
لكن معظم المحللين أساؤوا تشخيص المرض.
They say that corruption is the result of the one-party system,
يقولون أن الفساد جاء نتيجة نظام الحزب الواحد،
and therefore, in order to cure it,
ومن ثم، لكي تُعالجه،
you have to do away with the entire system.
عليك أن تتخلص من النظام بأكمله.
But a more careful look would tell us otherwise.
لكن بنظرة أكثر دقة ستبين لنا خلاف ذلك.
Transparency International ranks China
منظمة الشفافية الدولية صنفت الصين في المرتبة
between 70 and 80 in recent years among 170 countries,
ما بين السبعين والثمانين في السنوات الأخيرة من بين 170 دولة،
and it's been moving up.
وهي تتقدم.
India, the largest democracy in the world,
الهند، أكبر ديموقراطية في العالم،
94 and dropping.
في المرتبة 94 ونزولاً.
For the hundred or so countries that are ranked below China,
بالنسبة للدول المائة أو نحو ذلك التي صُنّفت في مرتبة أقل من الصين،
more than half of them are electoral democracies.
أكثر من نصف تلك الدول هي ديموقراطيات انتخابية.
So if election is the panacea for corruption,
إذن، إن كانت الانتخابات هي علاج الفساد،
how come these countries can't fix it?
لماذا لا تستطيع تلك الدول معالجته؟
Now, I'm a venture capitalist. I make bets.
حالياً، أنا مستثمر مغامر. أنا أعمل رهانات.
It wouldn't be fair to end this talk without
لن يكون منصفاً أن أُنهي هذا الحديث من دون
putting myself on the line and making some predictions.
أن أخاطر وأن أتنبأ ببعض التنبؤات.
So here they are.
وها هي.
In the next 10 years, China will surpass the U.S.
في السنوات العشر القادمة، ستتفوق الصين على الولايات المتحدة
and become the largest economy in the world.
وستصبح أكبر اقتصاد في العالم.
Income per capita will be near the top
دخل الفرد سيقترب من المرتبة الأعلى
of all developing countries.
لكل البلدان النامية.
Corruption will be curbed, but not eliminated,
سيتم الحد من الفساد لكن لن يتم القضاء عليه،
and China will move up 10 to 20 notches
وستتقدم الصين من عشرة إلى عشرين درجة
to above 60 in T.I. ranking.
إلى أعلى من ستين في تصنيف منظمة الشفافية الدولية.
Economic reform will accelerate, political reform will continue,
الإصلاح الاقتصادي سيتسارع، والإصلاح السياسي سيستمر،
and the one-party system will hold firm.
ونظام الحزب الواحد سيتمسك بموقفه.
We live in the dusk of an era.
نحن نعيش في ظلمة عصر من العصور.
Meta-narratives that make universal claims
القصص الكبرى التي تدعي ادعاءات عالمية
failed us in the 20th century
خذلتنا في القرن العشرين
and are failing us in the 21st.
وتخذلنا في القرن الواحد والعشرين.
Meta-narrative is the cancer
القصص الكبرى هي السرطان
that is killing democracy from the inside.
الذي يفتك بالديموقراطية من الداخل.
Now, I want to clarify something.
الآن، أريد أن أوّضح أمراً ما.
I'm not here to make an indictment of democracy.
أنا لستُ هنا كي أتهم الديموقراطية.
On the contrary, I think democracy contributed
على النقيض من ذلك، أعتقد بأن الديموقراطية ساهمت
to the rise of the West and the creation of the modern world.
في صعود الغرب وتكوين العالم الحديث.
It is the universal claim that many Western elites
إنه الإدعاء العالمي الذي تدّعيه العديد
are making about their political system, the hubris,
من النخب الغربية حول نظامهم السياسي، الغطرسة،
that is at the heart of the West's current ills.
التي هي أساس علّة الغرب الحالية.
If they would spend just a little less time
لو أنهم ينفقون القليل من الوقت
on trying to force their way onto others,
على محاولة شق طريقهم نحو الآخرين،
and a little bit more on political reform at home,
ووقت أطول قليلاً على الإصلاح السياسي في ديارهم،
they might give their democracy a better chance.
فقد يمنحون نظامهم الديموقراطي فرصة أفضل.
China's political model will never supplant
نموذج الصين السياسي لن يزيح أبداً
electoral democracy, because unlike the latter,
النظام الديموقراطي الإنتخابي، لأنه بخلاف الأخير،
it doesn't pretend to be universal.
لا يتظاهر بأنه عالمي.
It cannot be exported. But that is the point precisely.
لا يمكن تصديره. لكن هذه هي الفكرة بالضبط.
The significance of China's example
أهمية المثال الصيني
is not that it provides an alternative,
لا تتمثل في أنه يقدم نظام بديل،
but the demonstration that alternatives exist.
لكن تتمثل في إثبات وجود بدائل.
Let us draw to a close this era of meta-narratives.
دعونا نقترب من نهاية هذه الحقبة من القصص الكبرى.
Communism and democracy may both be laudable ideals,
الشيوعية والديموقراطية قد تكونا على حدٍ سواء نموذجان حميدان،
but the era of their dogmatic universalism is over.
لكن عصر شموليتهما الجازمة انتهى.
Let us stop telling people and our children
لنتوقف عن تعليم الناس وتعليم أطفالنا
there's only one way to govern ourselves
أنه لا يوجد إلا طريقة واحدة لنحكم أنفسنا
and a singular future towards which
ولا يوجد إلا مستقبل واحد الذي لا بد أن
all societies must evolve.
تتطور كل المجتمعات باتجاهه.
It is wrong. It is irresponsible.
هذا خطأ وغير مسؤول.
And worst of all, it is boring.
والأسوأ، أنه ممل.
Let universality make way for plurality.
اسمحوا للعالمية أن تفسح مجالاً للتعددية.
Perhaps a more interesting age is upon us.
قد يتواجد عصراً أكثر إثارة على مقربة منا.
Are we brave enough to welcome it?
هل نحن جسورين بما يكفي للترحيب به؟
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thanks.
أشكركم، شكراً لكم، شكراً لكم. شكراً.
Bruno Giussani: Eric, stay with me for a couple of minutes,
برونو غويساني: إريك، ابق معي لدقيقتين،
because I want to ask you a couple of questions.
لأني أريد أن أطرح عليك بعض الأسئلة.
I think many here, and in general in Western countries,
أعتقد أن الكثيرين هنا، وفي البلدان الغربية عامةً،
would agree with your statement about analysis
سيتفقون مع بيانك حول تحليل
of democratic systems becoming dysfunctional,
الخلل الوظيفي في النظم الديموقراطية،
but at the same time, many would kind of find
لكن في الوقت نفسه، سيجد الكثير أنه
unsettling the thought that there is an unelected
من المقلق نوعاً ما وجود سلطة حاكمة
authority that, without any form of oversight or consultation,
غير منتخبة التي، من دون أي شكل من الرقابة أو التشاور،
decides what the national interest is.
تقرر ما هي المصلحة الوطنية.
What is the mechanism in the Chinese model
ما هي الآلية في النموذج الصيني
that allows people to say, actually,
التي تتيح للناس قول، في الواقع،
the national interest as you defined it is wrong?
المصلحة الوطنية كما عرفتها خاطئة؟
EXL: You know, Frank Fukuyama, the political scientist,
إريك: أنت تعلم، فرانك فوكوياما، العالِم السياسي،
called the Chinese system "responsive authoritarianism."
أطلق على النظام الصيني اسم "الاستبداد المتجاوب."
It's not exactly right, but I think it comes close.
هذا ليس صحيحاً تماماً، لكن أعتقد أنه مقارب.
So I know the largest public opinion survey company
أعرف أكبر شركة لاستطلاع الرأي العام
in China, okay?
في الصين، حسناً؟
Do you know who their biggest client is?
هل تعرف من هو أكبر عملائهم؟
The Chinese government.
إنها الحكومة الصينية.
Not just from the central government,
ليس فقط من الحكومة المركزية،
the city government, the provincial government,
وحكومة المدينة، وحكومة المقاطعة،
to the most local neighborhood districts.
إلى أكثر الأحياء المجاورة محلية.
They conduct surveys all the time.
إنهم يجرون استطلاعات على الدوام.
Are you happy with the garbage collection?
هل أنت راضٍ عن جمع القمامة؟
Are you happy with the general direction of the country?
هل أنت راضٍ عن التوجه العام للحكومة؟
So there is, in China, there is a different kind of mechanism
إذن، هناك، في الصين، يوجد آلية من نوع مختلف
to be responsive to the demands and the thinking of the people.
للاستجابة لمطالب وتفكير الشعب.
My point is, I think we should get unstuck
فكرتي هي، علينا أن لا نتشبث
from the thinking that there's only one political system --
بفكرة أن هناك نظام سياسي واحد فقط --
election, election, election --
انتخابات، انتخابات، انتخابات --
that could make it responsive.
التي يمكن أن تجعله نظام متجاوب.
I'm not sure, actually, elections produce
لست متأكداً، في الواقع، أن الانتخابات تنتج
responsive government anymore in the world.
حكومة متجاوبة بما يكفي في العالم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
BG: Many seem to agree.
برونو غويساني: يبدو أن الكثير يتفقون معك.
One of the features of a democratic system
أحد خصائص النظام الديموقراطي
is a space for civil society to express itself.
هو توفير مساحة للمجتمع المدني ليعبر عن نفسه من خلالها.
And you have shown figures about the support
وقد أظهرت أرقام حول الدعم
that the government and the authorities have in China.
الذي تحظى به الحكومة والسلطات في الصين.
But then you've just mentioned other elements
لكنك بعد ذلك ذكرت عناصر أخرى
like, you know, big challenges, and there are, of course,
مثل، كما تعلم، التحديات الكبيرة، وهناك، بالطبع،
a lot of other data that go in a different direction:
الكثير من البيانات التي تذهب في اتجاه مختلف:
tens of thousands of unrests and protests
عشرات المئات من الاضطرابات والمظاهرات
and environmental protests, etc.
والاحتجاجات البيئية، الخ.
So you seem to suggest the Chinese model
يبدو أنك تلمح أن النموذج الصيني
doesn't have a space outside of the Party
لا يحظى بمساحة خارج "الحزب"
for civil society to express itself.
للمجتمع المدني ليعبر عن نفسه.
EXL: There's a vibrant civil society in China,
إريك لي: يوجد في الصين مجتمع مدني نابض بالنشاط.
whether it's environment or what-have-you.
سواء كان في البيئة أو أمور أخرى.
But it's different. You wouldn't recognize it.
لكنه مختلف. لن تتمكن من فهمه.
Because, by Western definitions, a so-called civil society
لإنه، بحسب التعريفات الغربية، ما يُسمّى بالمجتمع المدني
has to be separate or even in opposition
يجب أن يكون منفصل أو حتى معارض
to the political system,
للنظام السياسي،
but that concept is alien for Chinese culture.
لكن ذلك المفهوم غريب على الثقافة الصينية.
For thousands of years, you have civil society,
لديك مجتمع مدني منذ آلاف السنين
yet they are consistent and coherent
ومع ذلك هم متسقين ومتماسكين
and part of a political order, and I think
ويشكلون جزء من النظام السياسي، وأعتقد
it's a big cultural difference.
أن هذا اختلاف ثقافي كبير.
BG: Eric, thank you for sharing this with TED. EXL: Thank you.
برونو غويساني: إريك، شكراً على مشاركتنا هذا مع TED. إريك: شكراً لك.